YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 3. National Administrative Office
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES VI. PUBLICITY
  In 1947 the Committee on Financing the National Board asked the John Price Jones Corporation to make a study of public relations, publicity, and fund-raising. The Jones Report identified a general lack of understanding of "the true significance of the movement" among YWCA staff and membership. It faulted the National Association for a lack of focus, making its work too difficult to describe with no overall "story line" on which the publicity could be hung. The National Association adopted some of the report's recommendations-more-or-less centralizing public relations responsibility in a Public Information Department that reported directly to the General Secretary. The Publications Department, which was developing plans for a post-War revival of the Woman's Press, remained a separate department.
  Another recommendation of the Jones report was the development of two annual national events to throw the work of the YWCA "into sharp focus," National YWCA Week highlighting activities in the U.S. and World Fellowship Week focusing on fund-raising for YWCA work overseas. Public Information coordinated these events, producing packets with such things as posters, press releases, suggestions for programs, and radio and film "spots."
  After a trial period, the National Association concluded that expansion of the publications program was not practical and the Woman's Press (the 'general interest' titles) was sold in 1952. During the next office reorganization in 1960-61, publications was combined with public relations to form the Communications Bureau.
  The Bureau continued to provide similar services to the Association. It was closely involved with celebrations of the 125th (1982) and 135th (1993-94) anniversary celebrations. In 1986, the National Association embarked on an Organizational Identity Program which resulted in a new logo and stricter guidelines for its use by all Community and Student Associations. Periodic reductions in national staff lead to a heavier reliance on outside public relations and marketing consultants in the 1980s and 1990s.
  1913- Special Worker, Finance
  1915-19 Publicity Secretary (under General Admin)
  1920-22 Publicity Department, General Administration
  1923-25 Publicity Department, Editorial and Publicity Division
  1925-35 Publicity Department, General Administration
  1935-42 Interpretation and Publicity section, Committee on National Support and Interpretation, General Administration
  1942-44 Public Relations, Committee for National Interpretation and Support, General Administration
  1945-47 Public Relations, General Administration
  1948-60 Public Information, General Administration
  1961- Communications Bureau
  1970- Communications
  c 1984 Communications/Public Relations Division, [1984-86]
  1992- Communications and Public Relations, Development and Public Relations Division
  1995-97 Public Relations Division
  1999- External relations
  Publicity Office materials consist of minutes, reports, correspondence, publications, newspaper clippings, and publicity kits dating from circa 1910 to 2000. The activities of the Publicity staff are not particularly well documented in the records. The minutes and reports provide a general overview and miscellaneous isolated files, such as one on a feature article from 1961 called "A Woman's Place is Everywhere!," give an glimpse of the way the office functioned. The YWCA was involved in a number of film projects over the years, but unfortunately the records only contain materials describing these projects. The earliest footage in the collection is dated 1970.
  Publicity's task to 'interpret' the Association was accomplished in large part through the publication of a variety of pamphlets, booklets, etc. The Publications filed in this section are general pamphlets about the YWCA and instructional materials for Associations. Publications that are about specific departments or programs are filed with the records related to those activities and departments. Publicity's especially close ties with Financial Development mean that its work is often well documented in that department's materials.
  Microfilmed materials include press releases and clippings about the National Board and staff members, about events such as National YWCA Day and Week; general information pamphlets; scripts for radio talks; and information for speakers to use when talking about the YWCA.
  Publicity materials can be found on the microfilm under:
  Public Information Committee
  Publicity Committee
  Public Information
  Public Information, Publications, and Publicity
  Speakers
  Original Format Records, circa 1910-2000, 2 linear feet
  Surviving paper records are especially spotty. They are arranged as follows: General and History, Minutes, Programs and Projects, Publications, Reports, Studies, and Training.
  Due to the close ties between Financial Development and Public Relations, those files should also be consulted, especially the Committee on National Support and Interpretation and the publications. They can be found in SERIES III.
  Other related materials can be found in General Administration in SERIES I, especially under Public Relations, Controversy, Correspondence (mailings to Associations) and Business Division.
  General brochures about the YWCA and newspaper clippings can be found in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  Public Relations staff contributed to many training materials, particularly those produced for orientations of staff and Board members. These are filed under SERIES II. Training and Personnel in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
  The impact of the YWCA's Public Affairs program on its public image is documented in files in SERIES III in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
  Promotional materials can be found in Association serials and in publications and gifts catalogs in SERIES VI. PUBICATIONS in RECORD GROUP 6.
  RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS contains photographs commissioned and collected for public relations use as well as scripted slide presentations, a filmstrip, and some scripts for filmstrips about the YWCA.
  RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS includes audio and video public service announcements, television press coverage of YWCA campaigns and events, audio for a 1980 slide presentation about the YWCA, and interviews with YWCA leaders on a variety of television programs dating from the early 1980s to 2000.
  Memorabilia and keepsake items marketed to raise public awareness of the Association are filed separately for preservation purposes, see ARTIFACTS list.
- SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Series Descriptions for historical and scope and content notes about this Series.
  - Conferences/Meetings/Summits (non-YW)
    - Women's Centennial Congress of 1940 (Box 129, Folder 1)
    - U.S. Department of Labor Womanpower Conference, 1955 (Box 129, Folder 2)
    - Congress of the Laity Conference, 1977-78 (Box 129, Folder 3)
    - 1985 World Conference of the UN Decade for Women, Nairobi, Kenya (Box 129, Folder 4)
    - March for Women's Equality/Women's Lives, 9 Apr 1989 (Box 129, Folder 5)
    - Woman's Work: Challenges to New York City for the 21st Century Conference, 1987 (Box 129, Folder 6)
    - United Nations Commission on the Status of Women meeting, 1990 (Box 129, Folder 7)
    - World Summit for Children, 1990 (Box 129, Folder 8)
    - United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women, Region 8 Preparatory Meeting, 1994 (Box 129, Folder 9)
  - Controversy
    - Attacks, general, 1920-33, n.d. (Box 129, Folder 10)
    - Labor
      - Labor and industrial conflict, 1931-40 (Box 129, Folder 11)
      - Labor Advisory Group, 1944-50 (Box 129, Folder 12)
    - Communism charges against YWCA
      - General, 1934-73 (Box 129, Folder 13-14)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1948-56, n.d. (Box 129, Folder 15)
      - Counterattack: The Newsletter of Facts About Communism, 1947-59 (Box 129, Folder 16)
      - Joseph Kamp, the Constitutional Educational League, and his pamphlet "Behind the Lace Curtains of the YWCA," 1948-56, n.d. (Box 129, Folder 17-18)
      - "The Red Streak in the Y.W.C.A." article in The Sunday School Times, May 1949 (Box 130, Folder 1)
      - Robert H. Williams, the Williams Intelligence Summary, and the article "YWCA Program Reads Like Guide for Communists," Nelda S. Cain (Mrs. Norman H.), Kate Roemer French (Mrs. Earl R.) and the YWCA of the Borough of Queens, ("Queens Charges")
        - General, 1947-52, n.d. (Box 130, Folder 2-3)
        - Newspaper clippings, 1947-48 (Box 130, Folder 4)
      - Phyllis Schlafly and the Alton (Illinois) Association, 1951-53 (Box 130, Folder 5)
      - Marian M. Strack, 1947 (Box 130, Folder 6)
      - Rose Terlin, 1939, 1946-50, n.d. (Box 130, Folder 7-8)
      - Community Associations: correspondence and reports
        - Central region (Box 130, Folder 9-15)
        - Eastern region (Box 130, Folder 16-17)
        - Southern region, 1950-56 (Box 131, Folder 1)
        - Western region, 1948-52, n.d. (Box 131, Folder 2-4)
      - Correspondence, general public, 1948-50 (Box 131, Folder 5)
      - "Citizen groups"
        - General, 1952-53 (Box 131, Folder 6)
        - Minute Women of the USA, 1952 (Box 131, Folder 7)
      - "Communist Front" Organizations
        - American Youth for a Free World, 1944-45 (Box 131, Folder 8)
        - World Federation of Democratic Youth, 1945-67, n.d. (Box 131, Folder 9-13)
        - World Youth Congress
          - First, 1936 (Box 131, Folder 14)
          - Committees in U.S., 1936-38 (Box 131, Folder 15)
          - Second, 1937-38 (Box 132, Folder 1)
          - Additional research, 1948 (Box 132, Folder 2)
        - World Youth Festival, Moscow, 1957-58 (Box 132, Folder 3)
      - Reference materials
        - General, 1927-53 (Box 132, Folder 4)
        - Committee on Un-American Activities, U.S. House of Representatives, 1946-57 (Box 132, Folder 5-6)
    - Racial Justice 'Sit-in' Student Demonstrations
      - National Board Action, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 7)
      - National Student Councils of the YMCA and YWCA: memos and reports, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence
        - National Board President letter to Presidents of Negro Colleges, Apr 1960 (Box 132, Folder 9)
        - Community Associations
          - Central Region, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 10)
          - Eastern Region, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 11)
          - Southern Region, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 12)
          - Western Region, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 13)
        - F.W. Woolworth Co., and S.H. Kress and Co., 1960 (Box 132, Folder 14)
      - Newspaper clippings, resource material, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 15)
      - Other Organizations, 1960 (Box 132, Folder 16)
    - Young Women Committed to Action Conference, establishment of Racial Justice fund, and Vietnam Moratorium (1969-70)
      - General and clippings, 1969-70 (Box 132, Folder 17)
      - Correspondence with Community Associations
        - Central Region, 1969-70 (Box 132, Folder 18)
        - Eastern Region, 1969-70 (Box 133, Folder 1)
        - Southern Region, 1969-70 (Box 133, Folder 2)
        - Western Region
          - General, 1969-70 (Box 133, Folder 3)
          - Long Beach, California: questionnaire, 1970 (Box 133, Folder 4)
    - Black Panthers: Joan Bird Bail fund, 1970 (Box 133, Folder 5)
    - 1970 National Convention: resolutions passed and Bogalusa (Louisiana) Association mailing, 1970 (Box 133, Folder 6)
    - Angela Davis: YWCA Statement of Concern
      - General, 1970-72 (Box 133, Folder 7)
      - Advisory Committee on the Angela Davis Trial and the YWCA Position, 1971-72 (Box 133, Folder 8)
      - Community Associations
        - Central Region, 1970-72 (Box 133, Folder 9)
        - Eastern Region, 1970-72 (Box 133, Folder 10)
        - Southern Region, 1970-71 (Box 133, Folder 11)
        - Western Region
          - General, 1970-72 (Box 133, Folder 12)
          - California
            - General, 1970-72 (Box 134, Folder 1)
            - C.C. Moseley, 1971 (Box 134, Folder 2)
      - Ad-hoc Committee on the Open Letter to YWCAs, 1971 (Box 134, Folder 3)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 134, Folder 4)
    - Amnesty for draft dodgers and army deserters, 1972-73 (Box 134, Folder 5)
    - Volunteerism, 1973-74 (Box 134, Folder 6)
    - Equal Rights Amendment: National Board meetings in unratified states and Leadership Development Center, 1981-82 (Box 134, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1968-82, 1989-2001 (Box 135, Folder 1-4)
    - Government agencies, 1970-86 (Box 135, Folder 5-8)
    - YWCA
      - Community Associations and Student Associations
        - General
          - 1967-93 (Box 135, Folder 9-10)
          - 1994-98 (Box 136, Folder 1-11)
          - 1999-2001 (Box 137, Folder 1-4)
        - Mailings ("Executive Bulletin," "Monthly Mailing," "Communique," "Consolidated Mailing")
          - 1971-Feb 1987 (Box 137, Folder 5-18)
          - Mar 1987-Jun 1989 (Box 138, Folder 1-22)
          - Jul 1989-Sep/Oct 1991 (Box 139, Folder 1-17)
          - Jan/Feb 1992-Mar 1994 (Box 140, Folder 1-11)
          - Jul/Aug 1994-Jul 1996 (Box 141, Folder 1-12)
          - Oct 1996-2001 (Box 142, Folder 1-13)
      - Convention, 1962-64, 1994-2001 (Box 143, Folder 1-3)
      - Corporate partnerships, 1998-2001 (Box 143, Folder 4)
      - Jewish Social Identity Group, 1996 (Box 143, Folder 5)
      - Latina Caucus, 1998-99 (Box 143, Folder 6)
      - Lesbian Caucus, 1995-97 (Box 143, Folder 7)
      - Metropolitan Seminars, 1994-99 (Box 143, Folder 8)
      - National Association of YWCA Executives (NAYE), 1995-99 (Box 143, Folder 9)
      - National Student YWCA, 1964-75 (Box 143, Folder 10-11)
      - Staff and National Board
        - 1907-12 (Box 143, Folder 12-14)
        - 1913-14, 1971-2000 (Box 144, Folder 1-3)
      - State and Regional Councils
        - General, 1994-98 (Box 144, Folder 4)
        - Multi-State Convocation, Fort Wayne, Indiana, 1998-99 (Box 144, Folder 5)
      - Strategic Planning Process, 1994-98 (Box 144, Folder 6)
      - Student YWCAs, 1996-98 (Box 144, Folder 7)
  - Events
    - Miscellaneous, 1997 (Box 144, Folder 8)
    - Celebration of "600," 27 Mar 1982 (Box 144, Folder 9)
    - ENCOREplus, miscellaneous, 1995-97 (Box 144, Folder 10)
    - International Women's Day Open House and Screening, 5 Mar 1998 (Box 144, Folder 11)
    - Memorial Services 'for those who served the National Board to whom death came'
      - General, 1949-90 (Box 144, Folder 12)
      - Order of service, 1970-91 (Box 144, Folder 13-14)
    - World YWCA Centenary, 1993-94 (Box 144, Folder 15)
  - Legal
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-2000, n.d. (Box 145, Folder 1)
    - Chronological correspondence with attorneys
      - William D. Murray, 1923-37, [RESTRICTED] (Box 145, Folder 2)
      - Reynolds, Richards, and McCutcheon, 1938-43 (Box 145, Folder 3)
      - Reynolds, Richards, Ely, and LaVenture, 1968-73, [RESTRICTED] (Box 145, Folder 4)
      - Donovan, Leisure, Newton & Irvine, 1972-82 (Box 145, Folder 5-6)
      - Schnader, Harrison, Segal & Lewis, 1988-2000 (Box 145, Folder 7-10)
    - Finance/billing, 1988-89, 1991, 1995-96, [RESTRICTED] (Box 145, Folder 11)
    - American Girls Service Center, Istanbul, Turkey, 1988-92, [RESTRICTED] (Box 146, Folder 1-3)
    - Braithwaite v. YWCA of the USA, 1998-99 (Box 146, Folder 4)
    - Burrell v. YWCA of the USA, 1990-93 (Box 146, Folder 5)
    - California Nonprofit Corporation Law, 1978-80 (Box 146, Folder 6)
    - Copyright
      - General, 1994-2000 (Box 146, Folder 7)
      - Action Audit for Change, 1994-95, [RESTRICTED] (Box 146, Folder 8)
    - Florida law re sales tax exemption, 1983-84, [RESTRICTED] (Box 146, Folder 9)
    - Frederick J. Pratt Trust: audit, 1992 (Box 146, Folder 10)
    - Hosannah Christian Fellowship lease cancellation, Leadership Development Center, 1988 (Box 146, Folder 11)
    - New York State Membership Corporation Law, 1946-55, n.d. (Box 146, Folder 12-13)
    - Tax exempt status: challenges to local associations, 1955-95 (Box 146, Folder 14-15)
    - Trademarks
      - Registrations and renewals
        - General, 1946-2000 (Box 146, Folder 16)
        - ENCOREplus, 1995-97 (Box 146, Folder 17)
        - PACT (Parents and Children Together), 1995-97 (Box 146, Folder 18)
        - Race Against Racism, 1997-98 (Box 146, Folder 19)
        - Week Without Violence, 1997-2000 (Box 146, Folder 20)
        - Y-Teen, 1947-98 (Box 147, Folder 1)
        - YWCA, 1946-2001 (Box 147, Folder 2)
        - YWCA and triangle, 1955-77 (Box 147, Folder 3)
        - YWCA TECHGYRLS, 2000 (Box 147, Folder 4)
      - Infringement, 1992-96 (Box 147, Folder 5)
      - Permissions to use
        - 1950-62 (Box 147, Folder 6-14)
        - 1963-64, 1982, 1988-89 (Box 148, Folder 1-5)
    - U.S. Civil Rights Act of 1964, 1965 (Box 148, Folder 6)
    - YWCA Membership policy, 1997 (Box 148, Folder 7)
  - Membership
    - General, 1994-95 (Box 148, Folder 8)
    - Membership Marketing Campaign
      - Request for proposals and correspondence, 1997-98 (Box 148, Folder 9)
      - Hill & Knowlton: correspondence and proposals, 1997-98 (Box 148, Folder 10-11)
  - Mission/Purpose
    - YWCA as a Christian Organization
      - General, 1965-96 (Box 148, Folder 12)
      - Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement
        - Preparation, 1963-64 (Box 148, Folder 13)
        - Meetings
          - Jul 1964 (Box 148, Folder 14)
          - Sep 1964-65 (Box 149, Folder 1)
        - Regional consultations, 1965-66 (Box 149, Folder 2-3)
        - Correspondence, 1965-67 (Box 149, Folder 4-7)
        - Study documents, 1959-69 (Box 149, Folder 8)
        - "Guides for Participation," 1965 (Box 149, Folder 9)
        - Rosters, 1964-66 (Box 149, Folder 10)
        - Post-Commission, 1967-74 (Box 149, Folder 11)
    - YWCA as a Women's Organization, 1966-99 (Box 149, Folder 12-13)
    - Inclusion of the phrase "by any means necessary": correspondence, 1988-95 (Box 149, Folder 14)
  - National Office/National Staff
    - General and miscellaneous
      - Office charters and description, 1959-89, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 1)
      - General, 1933-2000, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 2-3)
      - Affirmative Action
        - Plan, 1976 (Box 150, Folder 4)
        - Reports, 1974-90 (Box 150, Folder 5)
      - National Board Residence, 1933-34 (Box 150, Folder 6)
      - Survey of the National Board of the Young Women's Christian Associations, W.H. Leffingwell Co., 1918 (Box 150, Folder 7)
      - Travel, 1936-37 (Box 150, Folder 8)
      - Unemployment insurance, 1937-38 (Box 150, Folder 9)
      - Use of headquarters building by outside groups policy, 1937 (Box 150, Folder 10)
      - Use of union printers policy, 1927-52 (Box 150, Folder 11)
      - Worship, Commemoration, and Meditation Services, 1966-85 (Box 150, Folder 12)
    - Committees, Councils, Departments
      - Facilities management and clerical/business functions
        - Office Committee/Committee for the Office Department/Office Department: minutes, 1908-21 (Box 150, Folder 13-17)
        - Cafeteria Committee: minutes, 1916-21 (Box 151, Folder 1-2)
        - Business Division: minutes, 1921-29 (Box 151, Folder 3)
        - Headquarters Committee/Buildings Committee/Buildings and Catering Committee: minutes, 1912-33 (Box 151, Folder 4-9)
        - Headquarters Services Committee
          - 1933-49 (Box 151, Folder 10-17)
          - 1950-70 (Box 152, Folder 1-7)
        - Hospitality Committee: minutes, 1932-34 (Box 152, Folder 8)
        - Office Services Committee: minutes, 1942-52 (Box 152, Folder 9-11)
        - Property Management Committee, 1971-81 (Box 152, Folder 12)
        - Information Resource Management Committee, 1987 (Box 152, Folder 13)
      - Administration/Personnel/Standards of work
        - Committee on Relationships Between Home and Foreign Departments, 1908 (Box 152, Folder 14)
        - Office Conference and Office Council
          - History and Constitution, 1915-21 (Box 152, Folder 15)
          - Minutes, 1908-21 (Box 152, Folder 16-17)
        - Schedule Committee: minutes, 1923-29 (Box 152, Folder 18-19)
        - Evaluation Council, 1929 (Box 153, Folder 1)
        - Committee on National Board Personnel, 1932-33 (Box 153, Folder 2)
        - National Employed Personnel Committee, 1939-69 (Box 153, Folder 3-5)
        - National Personnel and Labor Relations Committee, 1973-79 (Box 153, Folder 6)
        - Staff Planning Group, 1978, 1980-81 (Box 153, Folder 7)
        - Service Coordinating Group, 1979-81 (Box 153, Folder 8)
        - Communications Task Force, 2000 (Box 153, Folder 9)
      - Staff Meetings
        - Secretaries [and Special Workers], 1908-17 (Box 153, Folder 10-12)
        - Office Executives and Office Secretaries meeting minutes, 1919-28 (Box 153, Folder 13)
        - Office Management Council/Office Supervisory Staff: minutes, 1944-57 (Box 153, Folder 14-18)
        - Professional and National Staff
          - 1930-56 (Box 153, Folder 19-20)
          - 1957-59, circa 1970-99 (Box 154, Folder 1-6)
        - Directors and Managers, 1988-89 (Box 154, Folder 7)
    - Publications
      - Articles on Office Efficiency by Margaret McKinlay (Box 154, Folder 8)
      - Staff policy and procedure manuals, 1924-99 (Box 154, Folder 9-12)
      - "From 9 to 4:45," supplementary information to staff manual, 1941 (Box 154, Folder 13)
      - Handbook: "For Those Who Write and Those Who Type," 1950, 1989, n.d. (Box 154, Folder 14)
      - Manual of Filing Procedure, 1941 (Box 154, Folder 15)
      - Your Newsletter, 1972-74 (Box 154, Folder 16)
    - Reports
      - Building management (Box 155)
        - General, 1912-41, n.d. (Box 155, Folder 1-3)
        - Chair, Buildings Committee, 1912-18 (Box 155, Folder 4)
      - Business Division, 1924-26 (Box 155, Folder 5)
      - Business Committee of General Administration, 1930-31 (Box 155, Folder 6)
      - Business Functions of the National Board, 1933 (Box 155, Folder 7)
      - Catering/Cafeteria/Food Service
        - General, 1920-26 (Box 155, Folder 8)
        - Cafeteria Committee, 1916-21 (Box 155, Folder 9)
      - Employment Secretary, 1920-21 (Box 155, Folder 10)
      - Hospitality, 1921-41 (Box 155, Folder 11)
      - Librarian, 1920-21 (Box 155, Folder 12)
      - Office Department/Office Services
        - General, 1908-26, 1935-39 (Box 155, Folder 13-17)
        - Chair, Office Committee, 1908-19 (Box 155, Folder 18)
      - Social Secretary, 1912-22 (Box 155, Folder 19)
    - Training
      - General, 1976-99 (Box 155, Folder 20)
      - National Staff Orientation, Jun 1986 (Box 155, Folder 21)
      - Support Staff Orientation, Apr 1987 (Box 155, Folder 22)
      - Professional Staff Orientation, Jun 1987 (Box 155, Folder 23)
      - Professional Staff Retreat: Improving Organizational Effectiveness, Sep 1988 (Box 155, Folder 24)
      - Support/Technical Staff Retreat, Dec 1988
        - Correspondence and notes (Box 155, Folder 25)
        - Handouts (Box 156, Folder 1)
        - Evaluations (Box 156, Folder 2)
      - In-Service Development Session on Racial Justice, Jan 1989 (Box 156, Folder 3-5)
      - Management Roundtable: Human Resources Skills Update, Dec 1994 (Box 156, Folder 6)
      - National Staff Orientation: Racism and Heterosexism, Mar 1996 (Box 156, Folder 7)
      - Customer Service Workshop, Feb 2000 (Box 156, Folder 8)
    - Union
      - General and history, 1946-72, n.d. (Box 156, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, and agreements, 1939-41, 1943-48 (Box 156, Folder 10-17)
      - Scrapbook of news clippings and materials distributed by United Social Agency Employees, Aug 1948-1949 (Box 157, Folder 1-2)